this is software engineering radio the
podcast for professional developers on
the web at se-radio.net
sc radio is brought to you by the ieee
computer society by ieee software
magazine
online at computer.org software
keeping your teams on top of the latest
tech developments is a monumental
challenge
helping them get answers to urgent
problems they face daily is even harder
that's why 66 percent of all fortune 100
companies count on o'reilly online
learning
at o'reilly your teams will get live
courses tons of resources
interactive scenarios and sandboxes and
fast answers to their pressing questions
see what o'reilly online learning can do
for your teams
visit o'reilly.com for a demo
welcome to software engineering radio
i'm akshay manchala and today i'll be
talking to tomo shiran
tomer is the chief product officer and
co-founder of premio
previously tomorrow led the product
management team at mapr
where he was responsible for product
strategy roadmap and requirements
prior to map r tomer held numerous
product management and engineering roles
at ibm
and microsoft tomer welcome to the show
thanks for having me here
awesome so before getting into data
lakes let's talk a little bit about the
history and how we got here
everyone is familiar with databases and
they've existed for many decades
but at some point you know there was a
transition and evolution to having data
warehouses in an organization
so can you talk about what what were the
motivations and what led to that
need to have a data warehouse sure yeah
you know back in the day it all started
with people having
databases where they were running their
applications or storing the data for
their applications and performing
transactions there
and there was a need to to analyze that
data and
for a couple of reasons you know
sometimes it became hard to
analyze the data on that operational
database
for reasons of you know first of all you
didn't want to impact the performance of
the application that was running and
that was potentially a mission critical
kind of oltp application and then also
in some cases you wanted to
kind of centralize data from multiple
places multiple sources
or multiple databases and be able to
analyze data
that's coming from from many sources and
so being able to move that data into
one place and ultimately that became the
the data warehouse
and i think in many cases data warehouse
technologically was just database it was
the same
type of technology that people were
using for their otp databases whether
that's a
you know oracle database or or something
else you know sql server and so forth
so that was kind of the rise of the the
data warehouse
yeah and from data warehouses and more
recently you know we've had a transition
to having data stored in different forms
you know you had structured data for the
most part and then you have unstructured
no sql like databases that started
coming about
so what was really the motivation there
and how does that contrast with respect
to
the data warehouse evolution before that
well i think there's two aspects here
you know the the nosql database
movement and technologies like mongodb
and inelastic search which you could
kind of put in that bucket
we're all around making the developer
more productive so
a lot of applications were being built
with you know json and
nested structures and it was easier to
represent kind of objects in the real
world using those structures as opposed
to kind of flattened out tables
and so that's the reason people started
building or companies came up with these
nosql databases like
mongodb which were much nicer i think
for for a developer to
to go build an application and then in
parallel i think there were also for
analytical
workloads a lot of data sources that
were you know maybe log files and
and other data that was wasn't
necessarily your traditional
kind of star schema all right very
structured
you know data that people were putting
in in data warehouses and databases and
so
you know i think that was another kind
of thing that drove the the rise of
these semi-structured data sets
right so agility i guess developer
agility was like a huge portion for that
that change coming from there you know
what what led to
the emergence of say data leaks and
looking at your data as a data lake
i think the early days of the data lake
were all about
the ability to kind of store larger
volumes of data and ingest larger
volumes of data
more easily into a centralized kind of
repository right if you think about the
the data warehouse a ton of effort goes
into you know creating those
those models creating the tables the
schemas making sure that the data that's
being ingested
you know meets those you know having to
change the schema before you actually
ingest any data so
pretty rigid and and takes a lot of
effort and so
the ones systems like hadoop back in the
day this is like 2009 2010.
once those were created the ability to
just you know have a
a repository where you can dump files
whether they're log files or more
structured data
into a single system and pay a very low
cost per terabyte
or gigabyte that was i think a big
motivation there i think what then
happened you know early on in the the
world of data lakes
you know a lot of the processing was was
this kind of batch processing right it
was
really designed for these map-reduced
jobs originally this is pre-spark
and pre kind of being able to run sql on
the on data lakes
but one of the the really interesting
things that
kind of came out of this is the creation
of many different types of
computational engines right so the
ability to
use one engine for a developer that
wants to do kind of batch processing
right something like spark and a
different engine for somebody
or kind of workloads that are more like
a interactive sql and bi right that's
that's what we do at dremeo so all sorts
of different engines you know different
machine learning engines that all
interact with that same data
that i think has become the defining
feature
of the data lake which is something you
you just can't get in
in a data warehouse right i guess the
separation of the compute and storage
aspects of it really led to the
emergence of various compute
aspects but on the storage side was
there is it still hadoop and hdfs or how
do people look at a data lake is there a
classic data lake product
so to speak i think now for us
what we see is the vast majority of data
lake
projects are actually in the cloud and
so once companies started
moving to the cloud and things like aws
and azure right where you have
these storage services like s3 which is
infinitely scalable
and very inexpensive you know it's 20
dollars per terabyte or less and
you don't have to manage much you only
pay for what you use you know it's it's
just and it's
it's available geographically in many
different regions
around the world so you have a much
better solution now for for the storage
of a data lake
in the cloud and you know the same thing
in the other cloud providers
for example adls on on azure so that's
created
really a much more powerful concept and
you know this is now being taken
advantage of by
both cloud data warehouses and cloud
data lakes and so the cloud data
warehouses take advantage of
the fact that you have this separate
kind of infinitely scalable storage
system
but they separate the compute from the
from the storage
but the data itself is still stored in a
proprietary format that is you know tied
to that one data warehouse and
and you know can't be accessed by other
computational engines you have to pay
that data warehouse vendor to get the
data in to
to get it out to anytime you want to do
something with it whereas with cloud
data lakes
what happens is that the data inside of
these storage systems like s3
is stored in open formats right open
source formats like parquet is a column
or format that's high performance and
increasingly also open table formats
like
things like apache iceberg and delta
lake and by having the data stored in
open formats
that can be accessed and transacted uh
on from
different systems right you know dramio
being being one of these systems but you
can use uh
you know other engines that are out
there you can spark use databricks you
need presto athena
there's a lot of different engines and
tools that can interact with the same
data
and so you're not locked into one
specific uh
data warehouse vendor is there a
particular defining characteristic that
you see for a data lake is it the
variety of data is it the volume of data
is there a single defining
characteristic that you would you
normally see
well i think data lakes typically are
used in situations
where companies have relatively large
volume of data so you typically see this
being used by either enterprises so
larger companies
and they typically have a lot of data or
you often see this even with smaller
companies that are tech companies so
venture backed
technology companies where you know
they're they're
they may be a small company of maybe a
couple hundred people but they're
serving millions of users right because
you know that's just the nature of their
business and so they're generating a lot
of data and have
have the need to analyze a lot of data
as a result of that so
that's i would say typically the
defining kind of
element of a a data lake historically
there's been talk about you know back in
the days of hadoop people talked about
well you should use the data like if you
have unstructured data semi-structured
data
things like that i think these days most
of the data that people use is
structured data
so it's it's not like okay people that
have structured data are putting that in
a
database and people have unstructured
use data like it's actually the vast
majority of use cases where we see
people using data lakes the data
structure it's in tables that have you
know rows and columns and schemas and
you know and they're doing processing on
that that data so that's really no
longer a big distinction
i think so before you actually have data
stored
in say s3 or something you may have data
in different databases maybe it's in
their warehouse
what's really the ingestion path into
say
s3 what sort of etl tools do people
normally use to get their data in
so i think i think you can look at the
the data that's out there
and kind of think of it as two different
categories one is
data that's uh being generated in say
operational databases
these are the you know the otp
relational databases you know oracle sql
server and it's the nosql databases like
mongodb
and that data needs to be you know
ingested into uh
into s3 and then you have especially for
companies that were born in the cloud or
new
new applications are being built in the
cloud a lot of the data exhaust from
those systems
kind of natively just lands in you know
starts its life in s3
you know fortunately what what's
happened is and this is thanks to the
i think the value proposition the
benefits of of systems like s3 that are
you know so inexpensive and infinitely
scalable they've become the de facto
system of record in the cloud right this
is where everybody puts their data even
you know you look at companies that use
data warehouses in the cloud
the vast majority of them probably over
90 percent the data is actually first
starting first being moved into
s3 and then from there loaded into a
data warehouse and that's because it's
so inexpensive and so easy to
put the data into s3 i'd say a lot of
companies
you know it's it's very simple to kind
of upload data into s3 so they just kind
of do it themselves they
they write some some code from you know
in python use some amazon tools
others use etl tools to to do that so
every etl tool basically now supports uh
getting data into s3 whether it's the
more traditional etl tools
you know informatica talon some of these
newer data pipeline tools you know five
trend material
you know stitch etc so there's a lot of
different options for for people to get
data into s3 these days
well sv itself is kind of like an object
store right so how do you catalog and
organize your data if you have a
database it's fairly straightforward you
have a schema that defines like what
sort of tables you have and then you
have the
the actual columns within it also well
defined whereas in s3 you're just
talking about a single file right so
what's what's the cataloging and
organization there
sure so so you're right s3 is is at its
core it's an object or
a file store right so you're just doing
files and so there's just
really two ways to kind of define maybe
maybe let's let's call it three ways to
define
a table in this kind of a system so the
most
simple but maybe least flexible way is
is you know you store the files in kind
of a self-describing form
right so you just drop a bunch of files
in a directory all these files are in a
format like uh
you know parquet apache parque or maybe
even just you know json files
and you know because those are
structured and many engines you know
like driving you can
just you know point at that read that
query that right and if you structure it
well you can also even support
partitions right by having kind of
nested
directory path so that's one way um the
second generation
that was created kind of uh on top of
that is
systems like hive metastore and amazon's
glue catalog
so these systems provide kind of a
a metadata layer or kind of a
description layer
on top of those files right so now you
have
uh rather than just you know pointing at
a specific path
and that's your table this metastore or
catalog
hive metastore or glue they basically
store the definitions of all these
tables and for each table they they
store the schema and they also store
kind of the list of files that make up
that table so it's kind of a separate
system
and that's great ads a lot of structure
makes it easier to be have kind of
consistent definition of tables across
different systems
you know one of the challenges there was
just the scalability of those systems
and also the fact that they're kind of
disconnected from the data itself so you
have kind of
the the files being stored on s3 but you
have the
the data being or the metadata being
stored in a separate system
that that is transactional and so it's
hard to kind of do anything uh
kind of transactional that way and so
what you've seen in the last year
is the rise of these table formats
native table formats that are
transactional
and you know support data mutations and
support time travel
directly on systems like s3 and so you
have two real
i'd say two main kind of competing
technologies there you have
one project is called delta lake it was
created by databricks and
primarily supported by their system
although that data can be queried from
other systems like
you know like dremeo and others and then
i think more
more relevant is apache iceberg which is
a project created by netflix
and now backed by apple and you know
airbnb and stripe and
adobe and alibaba and basically many of
the largest
tech companies are now behind the apache
iceberg
and the idea there is to have an open
source table format that supports
transactions
supports record updates and and
deletions
supports time travel and allows these
types of transactions to happen
from basically any engine whether it's
uh dremeo or spark or
or any other engine out there they can
all perform transactions and updates on
the data
and do that in a consistent way without
you know kind of harming each other
so iceberg sort of uses s3 as a backing
storage system
through which you can push data in is
that right
yeah so iceberg you can think of iceberg
as basically uh it has manifest files
basically files that describe the data
that are stored alongside the data so in
s3 you have a file that basically
points to what are the data files and
also includes information about the
schema
and it does it in a way that when an
update is made it doesn't lose the
previous version it kind of
only it keeps track of the delta so
there's a new manifest file
and then you kind of the root pointer
points to the new manifest file
and that allows you know different
engines to support transactions and
and version control on this data
interesting
so i i want to dig into some of the
storage formats a little more you know
we
started with say xml and json was super
popular
early on in the decade due to uh the
whole nosql storage
systems now you have uh parquet avro
a couple of these formats so can you
walk us through some of those newer
emerging formats and what they're
really used for yeah i think
if you want to call you know xml and
then you know json as as kind of
that first generation i think the focus
there was on interoperability
on having a standard that you know
different systems can can talk to right
and of course json being much simpler
much more elegant i think than
xml and back in the day i was you know
starting my career as an engineer at ibm
i was
uh i was totally immersed in this world
of xml you know i was using these
xml spy tools and i was i could create
xsds
uh you know while i was asleep so that
was that was the
standard back then and that that's
improved but when you think about
analytics it's not
it's not just about storing the data in
a way that's interoperable and and
you know can be understood by different
technologies it's also about performance
right you can't just uh you can't store
it in kind of a text format like json or
or xml because that's not going to be
very efficient for querying
and so then you saw the rise of these
newer formats and avro and parque are
examples of that orc is another example
and there kind of the world separates
into two different formats there's
there's the
row base or row oriented formats where
you know kind of from a binary
standpoint
each each record is stored you know the
first record is stored before the second
record which is stored before the third
record so you kind of you have
all the data for that that first row
before all the data the second row and
so forth
and then you have the column formats
where the data is structured in the
you know column by column so you know
maybe take the first uh
you know 1000 records of the data set
and store the
the name column for each of those 1000
records followed by the
you know the ages of all the 1000
records followed by the you know the
address of
of those 1000 records and so that's
that's what's called the columnar format
so parque is a culinary format
and that has a lot of advantages in
terms of things like compression for
example you can you can
be much more efficient in terms of
how well you can compress the data if
you're storing for example
all the dates right one after the other
right you can use things like delta
encoding and so forth
and then it also has another benefit uh
when you're using a
a columnar format in that when you think
about query processing
we once did a study of some of our
largest
some of the largest dremel customers
some of the largest banks in the world
in tech companies
and what we saw is that on average five
percent of the columns
of a given data set are actually being
queried right in
on on a regular basis so you have these
data sets that have a thousand columns
in them or 500 columns in them
and out of those 500 columns you know
maybe
20 of them or or you know 25 of them are
actually being queried
right by by the users the rest are yeah
they're stored there for for
reasons of wanting to maintain that data
but nobody's accessing them so if you
think about
doing query processing the ability to
only read from disk or only read from s3
the data that's applicable to that query
can save you a lot of time right in
terms of
how fast you can actually process that
data and run the query so let's say
you're a business with a standard
traditional database right and you want
to
push that data into your s3 like data
lake
storage system how do you manage
ingestion
in terms of data quality you could have
multiple databases within the
organization
uh so data quality is really important
with respect to how you're pushing that
data into your data lake right so what's
the admission control
look like you know there's not one
magic in you know solution or an
ingredient to
achieving data quality or ensuring data
quality because at the end of the day
it's a business
problem right it's something that's a
custom problem to to
your situation as a as a company right
and the cleanliness how clean the data
sets are
and the same problem and it's no
different really if you think about it
from
you know data lakes data warehouses you
have the same challenges regardless
right but uh one big trend i think that
has happened
in the last few years is a shift from
what was called etl or extract transform
and load which would was how you know
you kind of got data into like data
warehouses to
now everybody's doing elt which is
extract load and transform right so the
order change the
the transform that the t went from being
the middle to being the end
and the reason for that if you think
about it that when it was etl
what was happening is that you had these
tools like say informatica or even just
scripts
that were actually doing this
transformation as the data was being
moved from the source system
into like the data warehouse or the data
lake and
that has all sorts of challenges right
first of all the the fact that
you know these etl tools they can't
scale anywhere near the same level as
you know your data warehouses or your
data lakes right so as soon as data
volumes got big
and that typically didn't work also you
know being able to kind of reproduce or
go back to that raw data
and being able to change the
transformation or or figure out what
went wrong
becomes harder and so you know for most
companies now the the standard is
uh is elt for any any new kind of use
case and so what you do there is you
take the data from the source system
you pretty much dump it into something
like s3
and the great thing is because also s3
and adls and
all these kind of cloud storage systems
are so inexpensive and so easy
you don't have to worry as much about
the cost right when you're paying that
that little
so you're not worried about that you put
the raw data that you took from the
source system you put it inside of s3
and then you do that transformation and
then you
you know you clean the data so you don't
necessarily give everybody access to
that
raw dump of of your your database and
you do some transformations you clean
the data
maybe you apply some security policies
and then you expose that to to
kind of the users right so since you are
saying the
transformation is actually going to
happen towards the end i assume that
transactional nature of data is not
directly visible when you are
loading data into a data lake it's just
you dump it there and then later you
figure out what has happened
is is that typically how you go about
transactional data
well i i think what you're hitting on is
like data freshness right
like how fresh can can the data be so if
i'm taking data from a source system
putting in a data lake
well no matter what there's going to be
some latency right um when i take data
from one place and put in another place
for it to be queried but you do want to
shrink that that latency as much as
possible and so there's newer
newer approaches that a lot of companies
are using now and and also data
kind of pipeline technologies things
like kafka where for use cases that
require
kind of more real-time data a lot of
times they're being ingested that way as
opposed to kind of a
batch process from like a you know a
database
into just kind of batch jobs taking
chunks of data and putting them into the
data lake right so it really depends on
on the need there what we've found
though is that i'd say the majority of
use cases it's less about having the
last
one minute or last five minutes of the
data available for queries especially if
it's a human kind of use case where you
know somebody's going to actually look
at
the data for ad hoc analysis or kind of
maybe a business intelligence dashboard
what's more important is that you know
you're not
it's not taking you weeks or months
right to get this to work and
for any change to happen in the system
right that that's the
probably the bigger problem than okay if
everything were working and the only
problem was i can't see the last five
minutes of data
for most use cases that's okay not
always obviously if you're trying to do
fraud
fraud analysis or fraud detection you
know you may you may need obviously the
the
live kind of real-time data feed right
for this is great for analytics
one thing is now that you're actually
moving a lot of data from different
sources into a data lake
what is compliance like you know you
might have gdpr requests that say
i want all of my data to delete it now
you have it in various forms in various
places so
how do you conform to some of those
policies
at o'reilly we know your tech teams need
quick answers to their most urgent
questions they need to stay on top of
new tech developments
they need a safe place to learn the
technologies your company adopts
and they need it all 24 7. well they can
get it all at o'reilly.com
with o'reilly online learning your team
gets live online courses
tons of resources safe interactive
scenarios and sandboxes
and fast answers to their most pressing
questions
visit o'reilly.com and request a demo
from my perspective a key to having data
governance and
security is to to minimize the amount of
data copying that's happening
so if you think about the traditional
architecture even in the cloud
is companies they kind of they have
their data either being generated
directly on s3 or they're moving data
into s3
then they you know they take a subset of
that data they load into a data
warehouse
for querying then within the data
warehouse they create copies of that
data because different users and groups
have different needs around how to view
the data and also for performance
reasons right
you know the the raw data is too big in
the data warehouse so um the queries are
slow and so then you want to maybe
summarize
pre-aggregate or summarize it and create
kind of more filtered or aggregated
views
or tables of that data and then the
access often is too slow and so then
additional copies get created by
kind of creating you know bi exports if
you're using tools like tableau or
microsoft power bi you're creating
what's called exports or
or imports into the bi tool and if
you're a data scientist you're exporting
data from the warehouse
into like a local file on your laptop so
you can do data science and so
you can see in this whole pipeline
there's so many copies of data and
you know that makes it very hard indeed
to deal with things like gdpr
because somebody submits a request to
under the right to be forgotten right
they say yeah i want you to delete all
the records related to that person
well if that data has been copied all
over the place by different users it
becomes
basically impossible to really satisfy
that
in many ways the centralized kind of
data team doesn't even know where the
data is anymore
so that's been one of our focuses at
drameo we call it the no copy
architecture is to really minimize the
need for data copies
right you want to have one centralized
system that can support data
democratization
and give people the performance that
they need all the way from
you know of course the the kind of the
ad hoc you know experimental
data exploration kind of use cases but
all the way to that sub second
and kind of bi workloads that in the
past you'd have to
go through that all that complexity to
achieve these uh kind of bi
performance requirements yeah i want to
come back into uh premio and like you
know how you're doing this your copy
analytics but before we get there can
you talk through some of the
common use cases for a data lake that
you see in the industry today
sure you know i think the the data lakes
are used
horizontally by in in really every
industry right so
when i think about the companies that we
deal with in the world of data lakes
it's everything from
you know the world's largest banks to
the largest insurance companies to you
know tech startups
it's really all over the place in terms
of the kind of the
industries and what they're doing with
the data but
the common thing there is that the
companies have a lot of data and they're
trying to get value out of that data
right they're trying to process that
data they're trying to
query that data and present it in
dashboards they're trying to do machine
learning on that data so they have a
variety of different
workloads that they want to bring to
that same data
all right and that's one of the one of
the advantages of the data lake is that
you know that's
the same set of data and this is why the
it's so beneficial to have this this
architecture where you have kind of the
data stored in open formats
the same set of data can be processed by
all these different engines
for different use cases so to give you
an example one of our customers is um
you know a tech company and they're you
know they're optimizing their supply
chain
right so they have a lot of data from
you know all sorts of all parts of the
kind of the supply chain and they need
to be able to
visualize this and present this to all
the way from the folks that are
responsible for understanding what's
happening in the supply chain and where
the bottlenecks all the way to the
executives that are looking for kind of
a bigger picture
you know how are we doing how many units
have we moved and so forth and being
able to do that
requires you to be able to
aggregate the data and provide that big
picture view of it very very quickly
because that executive that wants to log
in and look at a dashboard
they need a response with less than a
second and it also requires the ability
to drill down into the detail level data
right so down to individual records and
what happened to this
you know what happened to this box and
and so forth right so
um so it goes all the way down down to
that but yeah in many in many cases
we're talking about
a variety of different use cases all
kind of being executed on that same
that same data you know there's a lot of
value to be extracted and
you could be in an organization that is
having a lot of data from
various sources inside of a instead of
your data lake and how do you go about
exploring what's actually available is
there any exploratory tools to kind of
discover
the kinds of data that you have that
might lead to richer analytics
yeah there actually are in fact there
are companies that vendors that this is
this is what they do they
they they've developed these data
catalogs right so you know companies
like colibranolation and
and others that uh this this is exactly
what they do they try to
kind of surface the the meta information
right the descriptions of the data
sets they provide maybe a search bar
that allows you to
you know search for you know if you know
kind of what you're looking for hey i'm
looking for sales data i'm looking for
things like that then you put in the
search bar it will surface tables that
maybe have that
column or the columns can be described
and also uh
you know you can have tags on these
different things so it gives you a level
of kind of data management and
kind of a catalog that you can explore
what you have and then i think for most
companies it comes down to a wiki to be
honest
at the end of the day there's a lot of
tribal knowledge this is a problem that
has never been truly solved to the end
and i think there's a lot of tribal
knowledge and a lot that you can learn
from from other people within the
organization and you see a lot of that
obviously happening as well because yeah
there's descriptions of data but they
get
out of date and you know as the data is
changing and
you know you don't really understand
maybe what exactly is stored in that
table so
this is where it's important for the
company to have kind of really good data
management kind of processes as well
it's not just the tools
okay now i want to switch gears a little
bit and talk about premiere which is
obviously the company that you've
started so what is tremeo and how does
that fit into the ecosystem
yeah sure so we described dremeo as a
data lake service or a next-generation
data lake service
and the idea really is to bring kind of
the capabilities that you would
traditionally
have in a data warehouse to bring that
directly to the data lake and allow
people to
run sql queries directly on their data
in
systems like s3 and adls and so
really what we do is we we help
companies take advantage of all that
data they have in their data lake
not just for kind of the data scientists
that are doing ad hoc and kind of
exploratory work
but for the full spectrum of use cases
that you can accomplish with sql so
we're the sql engine
for the data lake and that ranges from
you know people that are using power bi
and tableau and they want that sub
second response time on their dashboards
all the way to people that are doing ad
hoc queries and kind of one
running one query at a time and you know
for many minutes and
and kind of exploring the results of
those queries
so we um we're the sql layer for
many of the world's largest data lakes
the largest uh many of largest banks in
the country and
largest tech companies retailers
insurance companies so it
really spans every vertical
so something that i read on when i was
going through some of the talks was
about virtual data sets that you can
create uh can you
tell us more about what virtual data
sets are sure
so you could think of the value
proposition of dramio as
uh having two key more than two but
let's talk about two key kind of
components one is
that performance element the fact that
we can you know run queries and achieve
that performance that typically
you know you couldn't get on a data lake
historically and then the second thing
is
what we call a semantic layer and so the
idea here is that
in a company that has lots of users that
want to consume data and increasing that
that's really every company because
everybody wants to democratize data and
and put it at the in the hands of of the
business
um you want to be able to make the data
accessible and consumable and secure
right and you don't want to create lots
of different copies for every single
user in the company
right so so we have these virtual data
sets where you can very easily create
kind of
different views of the data you know
whether it's uh it could be as simple as
renaming a column of a data set
all the way to you know masking a
specific column
for pi that has pi information or
you know cleaning the data or or joining
it with something else but
you create these virtual data sets and
that becomes kind of that semantic layer
and then regardless of what tool you're
using to access the data if it's a
tableau or power bi
or it's a jupyter notebook if you're a
python user you're basically seeing the
same definitions the same
virtual data sets regardless of how
you're accessing that data
and that makes it very very easy for
like the data team
and you know the data engineers to
provision data sets for different users
right they don't have to go and create a
separate copy because creating the copy
is easy it's keeping it in sync later
is the hard thing right as data is
constantly coming in 24x7
you know once you start creating copies
you have to keep those data pipelines
going and make sure you have
many lines of availability on them and
and so forth because very difficult
so we create these virtual data sets and
just creating virtual data sets alone is
not enough because
sure you can create you know views in a
database but but then you know
you query them and and it's really slow
right because you know a lot of compute
is happening
kind of on the fly and so we kind of
complement that with something we call
data
reflections which is a a way in which we
materialize
you know view different different views
of the data so you can
imagine a data set that maybe has
billions or hundreds of billions of
records and you want to have different
views of that data
some are maybe aggregated already maybe
sorted in different ways
but you don't want the users to have to
know and guess
which version of the data they should
use should they use a pre-aggregated
version because they're
they only need aggregate level data
should they use this sorted version
because they're
doing a filter on a specific column
right
the users of the data the consumers of
the data they're never going to
understand
things at that level right they you know
as we talked about earlier just
just knowing which data sets you have in
the company that alone is hard enough so
let alone you know if you had like 50
different representations of that data
set
so what we do at dremeo is we take these
you know the users they they operate in
the logical world they think about kind
of the data sets and the virtual data
sets
and then our query optimizer basically
gets the
gets the query composite into a query
plan and basically
rewrites that query plan internally to
leverage these different data
reflections
automatically and transparently to the
user and so you get that performance
that
you could get from highly optimized data
structures
without having to understand any of that
when you say data reflections is that
something that's actually materialized
is that just a virtual representation of
sorts so you have two different things
you have
the virtual data sets and those are
those are kind of like
kind of like views in a database but you
know we provide a much nicer interface
for people to kind of view them and
interact with them
and then you have the data reflections
which are various materializations and
so you could think of
a reflection as kind of being like an
index in a in a database
right you know an index say if you if
you went to an oracle database or a
postgres database
and you created a table and you created
an index on it the index is a different
data structure right it's
maybe it's a b tree that has uh you know
that column
kind of a copy of that column but sorted
in a specific way and kind of with
pointers to
the different records right so an index
is an example of a materialization
a cube in in olap is an example of
another kind of materialization
right there's different kinds of
materializations that you can have
and they're all good for different
workloads but the idea is that if you
can take that complexity
away from the users and you can
automatically take advantage of the
existing materializations when somebody
runs a query
well then then you can make that a
reality really right it's not
you don't have all these problems that
you had back in the day with
all these old lap cubes that people
would have to build and then the users
would have to point their bi tool at
that cube
and the user wanted something it wasn't
in the cube and it took you know two
months for the it team to
you know refresh that cube and all those
problems basically go away
so it's kind of like a set service way
of getting to what you want and
on the compute side of things like what
other common tools or
common processes exist you know you have
your data lake you have
data coming in from various sources that
you're storing how else is it used
what sort of tools are used for what
kind of applications
uh when you say tools are you mean in in
the data lake itself
yeah i would think things that make use
of the data in in our data lake
yeah yeah so most of the time if you if
you look at the
companies that are using drama they're
not using dremeo alone
right that i mean part of the value of
the data lake is that ability to use
different
compute engines different tools on the
same data right the data stored in open
source formats and you can use
different different tools on that and in
fact uh
werner vogels from from amazon the cto
of amazon wrote a nice blog post about
uh kind of
why amazon is standardized internally on
data lakes and
talks about the fact that you have this
flexibility but also that you have the
flexibility for the future right because
you know as we know things evolve fast
there's new open source projects there's
new
you know technologies that come up and
you know this allows you to
tomorrow use a new type of engine on
that data right without having to you
know do some kind of migration of your
data
but today you have systems like spark
that people use on the data when it's
more about batch processing and machine
learning you have
dedicated kind of machine learning
libraries like desk you have
things like flink for kind of stream
processing you have kafka more for kind
of on the ingestion
pipeline so there's actually a variety a
large variety of tools that people use
um as well you have you know for example
there's other sql engines
you know dremeo you know which which is
uh
yeah the company that i that i founded
five years ago but uh
you have other sql engines you have hive
you have presto that some companies use
there's a
you know amazon has a kind of a
serverless version of
of presto but those are more kind of i'd
say for the
ad hoc and kind of exploratory use cases
only right
they can't provide the performance that
you'd need for kind of lower latency
at workloads and things like bi as well
what about security you know you have
different kinds of data now and
how do these compute engines uh respect
the access control
or other security related aspects of
your underlying data
this is where it helps to have kind of a
metastore or a catalog
for the data which is respected by the
different engines right so
you have things like hive metastore and
kind of glue catalog that can provide
permissions and then actually there's an
open source project that we uh we've
recently created called uh project
nessie
which you can think of it as a
next-generation meta store for uh
for data lakes which not just provides
kind of the schemas and the permissions
but also provides a
git like experience for the data where
you can have version control and
branching and cross table transactions
and
it really makes your data like look like
it's a git repository and so
all of these types of meta metastores
that are
accessible by by different engines for
the most part they're they're all open
source
you can define the permissions in these
systems right and also integrate with
your existing identity provider for for
the user identities right
whether it's azure active directory or
octa or something like that
so you described the metastore aspect of
it right so
one of the things that i'm wondering is
that you have data that's coming in from
the
over your sources in different formats
now
is enforcing some sort of like a meta
schema an anti-pattern with respect to
data lakes because you want this variety
to be present but you also want it to be
present in a way that's consumable
so at the end of the day the the
fundamental building block
for a data lake for any system really
for analytics is a table
right and so that's the level where you
want to define the permissions right you
you want to say well
this table or perhaps these columns are
accessible to these users and
in this table or these columns aren't
accessible to those users and so
i think that's really important right
especially these days where
security is such an important thing for
companies especially when when it comes
to sensitive data and pii
that you really have to have that right
and data lakes maybe in their kind of i
think early days 10 years ago there were
questions oh is this secure enough and
so forth but
you know these days you know all the all
the fortune 500
they're all everybody's running data
lakes you know in many cases in the
cloud so
all these problems have been uh have
been solved
so one of the things that i've seen
about data lakes is people refer to
a data swamp of sorts like you know your
data lake turns into a data swarm
so what's uh how do you prevent that
well first of all what's the data swarm
what point do you call that a data swamp
and how do you prevent that
i think this is a problem that you have
with with data lakes and data warehouses
actually right because
at the end of the day if you don't
manage what's in that environment
then people start creating all sorts of
kind of
derived data sets they don't keep them
up to date nobody knows what those data
sets are
and that's what i think people refer to
when they say
kind of data swamp right it also sounds
nice right lake in a swamp that
yeah i i think that's a it's fun to say
that
but yeah fundamentally i think that you
have this problem regardless of of
what system you're going to use this is
where i think we go back to that that
idea that if you can reduce the number
of copies in the system right for
example with that semantic layer that we
have with virtual data sets and
reflections
you know by not requiring you to create
a different copy for every user that
needs something a little bit different
and not requiring you to export data
from your lake into
the warehouse and you know into bi
extracts and and so forth
if you don't have to create all these
copies then you're going to have less of
that problem right you're going to have
an organized you know repository of data
sets really that
that is up to date and well documented
and you know people can access and get
value of
i want to talk about the operational
aspects how do you see
organizations running operations around
data lakes
you normally you would have say dbas
managing your database clusters maybe
and you have
another set of uh operational engineers
who are managing your analytics
side of things right so how is the
operational transformation happening at
companies in order to manage their data
as a data lake
i think there's typically you know a
data team in most companies that's
responsible for the
for the data lake often it's the same
team that's responsible for the the
data warehouses the company has so you
know by and large they're they're the
ones doing that
what is happening i think is that and
this is especially driven by
kind of the rise of the public cloud and
the ease of use that now comes with
you know systems like uh like drameon
and other sas services
in this space is just becoming easier
and easier to utilize these different
services on on the data
right so you don't you don't have that
same complexity that you used to have
with you know
big monolithic hadoop clusters where you
have 30 different open source projects
running on the same set of hardware and
you know you're constantly having to
tweak and deal with memory settings and
you know upgrades of software different
software components and keeping them
kind of compatible with each other you
know those types of problems go away
when you have
when you're running in the public cloud
because you have this separation
of data and compute right the the data
is stored on
s3 and open format so yeah you got to
manage data of course that does
that that never goes away but you have
to worry less about the compute
right so give you an example we have you
know in our aws edition
we automatically spin up the engines so
you can define different uh what we call
we call them engines but you can define
different engines for different groups
within the company you know the
marketing group and maybe the executive
dashboards that
they have their own engine and maybe
that's a medium-sized engine and the
other one's an extra large engine
but they're all running independently
and they all kind of spin up and spin
down dynamically based on the workload
and so they're not interfering with each
other you're not having to deal with all
this
kind of fine-grained tuning of resources
between these different workloads and
worrying about well did the
the data science intern run a big a
massive job that's going to impact
you know the ceo's dashboard right so
it's becoming a lot easier
and the amount of uh i'd say the amount
of data engineering
work or kind of operational work that
has to go into managing
managing these things is on the decline
so is that because like you have a
higher throughput from the storage
side so that you can just pin up compute
resources as necessary
especially in the public cloud well i
think it starts with the fact that
you know you have somebody's really
willing to rent you servers by the
by the second right and that's that's
you know amazon and microsoft
whereas on-prem you basically bought
servers and it took you three months to
get the boxes from
you know somebody like dell or hp and
you have to rack and stack them and so
you didn't have much
elasticity there right you couldn't just
say hey i need uh you know
10 servers for the next 10 minutes to
for this workload and then you know here
take it back i don't want to pay for the
the other 23 hours and you know 50
minutes of the day right
so it starts there just having the
ability to rent a compute infrastructure
but then it also comes with the fact
that you have that separate
storage uh service that is accessible
from all these different engines right
so
you know when you look at a dremel
environment that has you know multiple
engines for different workloads they all
have access to that same
s3 storage system and
and the ability to get kind of decent
throughput there but they also
you know when you look at some of the
more sophisticated systems like like
drameo we also have built
kind of caching technologies right so a
dremel engine doesn't have to go to s3
to get the same data again and again and
again we actually leverage the fact that
amazon ec2 instances have
ss very fast ssds or nvmes on them
and we can leverage these nvmes in a
kind of a distributed way
and to cache the data locally close to
the compute without the user even
knowing that's happening right because
the nvme
they just come with a box and and so
from the user's standpoint they're just
getting
you know faster i o than they'd get if
we had to go to s3 every time
they're getting lower latency and also
lower cost because you actually
end up paying less for like ec the s3
get kind of gets inputs
so i want to start wrapping things up
and uh what are some
big obstacles and challenges that you
see in the whole data management space
going forward
so the challenges and opportunities for
for data lakes
is really to continue to push the
envelope in terms of kind of what's
possible from a data management
standpoint
and so historically you kind of had a
trade-off between data lakes and data
warehouses
as some you know as a company that was
building your data infrastructure
you could get the the scalability the
low cost
the flexibility you know the openness of
a data lake
or you could get the kind of the
all-in-one
kind of functionality the transactions
the the data mutations time travel that
you get with with the data warehouse and
that came at a very high cost and lack
of flexibility
and so forth what's happening now in the
world of data lakes is that
where companies like dremeo are
basically taking that trade off and
eliminating that trade-off
right basically bringing the the
functionality of the data warehouse to
to the data lake so that ability to have
you know transactions and
record level mutations you know dml
the ability to have time travel to query
the data as it was yesterday at 9am
all of that within the data lake so that
you no longer have to move your data out
of the data like into a data warehouse
for any
any kind of use cases and so i think if
you look at
fast forward you know a year or two from
now basically data lakes will
be solving all these use cases and there
will be less and less of a need for for
a data warehouse out there
i think that's the big big opportunity
and then you see
things things that are beyond that of
course with some of the newer innovation
things like uh
project nessie which are providing that
get like experience for for the data
lake
i think that also takes it kind of to
that next level enables things that
really weren't possible before across
any system
yeah that's that's definitely very
exciting all right so thank you so much
for coming on this here
tomorrow this is akshay munchale for
software engineering radio
yeah thank you it's been great to be
here keeping your teams on top of the
latest tech developments is a monumental
challenge
helping them get answers to urgent
problems they face daily is even harder
that's why 66 of all fortune 100
companies
count on o'reilly online learning at
o'reilly your teams will get live
courses
tons of resources interactive scenarios
and sandboxes
and fast answers to their pressing
questions see what o'reilly online
learning can do for your teams
visit o'reilly.com for a demo
thanks for listening to sc radio an
educational program brought to you by
ieee software magazine
for more about the podcast including
other episodes visit our website at
se radio.net to provide feedback you can
comment on each episode on the website
or reach us on linkedin
facebook twitter or through our slack
channel at
scradio.slack.com
you can also email us at team
sc-radio.net
this and all other episodes of sc radio
is licensed under creative commons
license 2.5
thanks for listening
you